<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A notable collection of diuers and so[n]dry places of the sacred scriptures which make to the declaratyon of the Lordes prayer, comenly called the Pater noster. Gathered by the famous clerke Master Peter viret, Frenchman. And translated oute of Frenche into Inglysh, by Anthony Scoloker. The .viii. daye of Iune. Anno. 1548.</title>
            <title>Bible. English. Selections.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119202</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854409</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854409</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19829</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14466)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19829)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 158:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A notable collection of diuers and so[n]dry places of the sacred scriptures which make to the declaratyon of the Lordes prayer, comenly called the Pater noster. Gathered by the famous clerke Master Peter viret, Frenchman. And translated oute of Frenche into Inglysh, by Anthony Scoloker. The .viii. daye of Iune. Anno. 1548.</title>
                  <title>Bible. English. Selections.</title>
                  <author>Viret, Pierre, 1511-1571.</author>
                  <author>Scoloker, Anthony, fl. 1548.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Anthony Scoloker. Dwelling wythout Aldersgate· And Wyllya[m] Seres dwellyng. in the Elye rentes in holborne. Cum gratia et priuilegio ad imprimendu[m] solum, per septennium,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Original French title not traced.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>A2r bears a subsidiary title: The places of Holye Scripture.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf bears printer's mark McK. 113.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19829:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19829:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>A Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble collection of diuers and ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places of the ſacred ſcriptures / which make to the declaratyon of the Lordes prayer / Comenly called the Pater noſter.</p>
            <p>Gathered by the famous Clerke Maſter Peter viret / Frenchman.</p>
            <p>And tranſlated oute of Frenche into In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſh / by Anthony Scoloker. The .viij. Daye of Iune. Anno. 1548.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> at London / by Anthony Scoloker. Dwelling wythout Alderſgate. And Wyllya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Seres Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng. In the Elye tentes in hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum Gratia et priuilegio ad Imprintum ſolum / Per Septennium.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19829:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19829:2"/>
            <head>The Places Of Holye Scripture / whyche make for the declaracion of the Lordes Prayer / Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munely called the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſter.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>Of the Prayer.</head>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:3"/>
               <p>Axe / and it ſhalbe geuen you. Seke / and ye ſhal fynd. Knocke / and it ſhalbe opened vnto you. For who ſoeuer aſketh receueth and he that ſeketh / fyndeth / and to hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knocketh / it ſhalbe opened. Mathew vij. b Ieremi .xxix. c. Iohn .xvi. c.</p>
               <p>And when thou prayeſt / thou ſhalt not be as the ypocrites are. For they loue to ſtande and praye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sinagoges / &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corners of the ſtreates / to be ſene of men. Verely I ſaye vnto you / they haue theyr rewarde. But when thou prayeſt / entre into thy Chambre / and ſhut thy doore to the / and pray to thy father which is in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret: and thy father whiche ſeeth in ſecret / ſhall rewarde thy openly. And when ye praye / bable not moche / as the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do: for they thynke that they ſhalbe heard for theyr moche bablynges ſake. Be not ye lyke them therfore. For your father kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth wherof ye haue nede / before ye aſke of hym. After thys maner therfore ſhall ye praye. Oure father which art &amp;c Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thew vi. b.</p>
               <p>Lykewyſe the ſpirite alſo helpeth our weakenes. For we knowe not what we ſhuld deſire as we ought: nevertheles the ſpirit it ſelf maketh interceſſion mightlye
<pb facs="tcp:19829:3"/> for vs wyth vnoutſpekeable groninges. Howe be it he that ſercheth the hart kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth what the minde of the ſpyryt is: for he maketh interceſſion for the ſayntes / ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the pleaſure of God. Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum .viij. d.</p>
               <p>Beleue me the tyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth that ye ſhal neyther vppon this montein nor at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem worſhyp the father. The time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth and is nowe alreadye / that the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in ſpiryt and in trueth. For the father wil ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſuch to worſhip hym. God is a ſpiryt / and they that worſhip him / muſt worſhip in ſpiryte and trueth. Iohn .iiij. c.</p>
               <p>For we are the circumcyſyon / euen we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſerue God in the ſpirite. Phil .iij. a. Alſo I ſhall praye wyth voyce / but I ſhal pray wyth vnd<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. Yet had I lever in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion to ſpeake five wordes with my vnd<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye enforme other alſo / rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne thouſand wordes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge i. Cor .xiiij. c.</p>
               <p>I wyl therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men pray in al places / lyfti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp pure ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out wrath or ſtrife i. Timoth .ij. b.</p>
               <p>Watch therfore at all tymes and pray Luke .xxi. g.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:4"/>
               <p>Pray alwaies with al maner of prayer &amp; ſupplycacion in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyrite. Epheſ .vi. c.</p>
               <p>I will always prayſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> everlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / his praiſe ſhalbe alwaies in my mouth. Pſal .xxxiiij. a.</p>
               <p>We reioyce before God of you / we pray ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cedi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly day and night .i. Theſſ .iij. b.</p>
               <p>Men ought alwaies to pray a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not to lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue of. Luke .xviii. a.</p>
               <p>Pray without ceaſing .i. Teſſ .v. d.</p>
               <p>Verely / Verely I ſaye vnto you what ſoeuer ye do aſke my Father in my name / he ſhal gyue it you. Iohn .xvi. e.</p>
               <p>The two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions whych are chefely required in prayer. Marc .xi. c.</p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer ye deſyre in your prayer / beleue that ye ſhall receyue it / and ye ſhal have it. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſtand and pray / for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue yf ye haue ought againſt anye man / that your father alſo in heauen / maye for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyue you your treſpaces.</p>
               <p>Our father</p>
               <p>We haue but one God / even the father of whome are all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs &amp; we in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .i. Cor .viii.</p>
               <p>I am the father of Iſraell Ierem .xxxi. I wyl be your father &amp; ye ſhalbe my ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:19829:4"/> doughters / ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almighty lorde ij. Cor .vi. d.</p>
               <p>Shuld not a ſonne honour his father / and a ſeruaunt his maſter? if I be nowe a father / where is my honour? if I be the lord where am I feared? Malach .i. b.</p>
               <p>Is ther any man among you which if his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne aſked hym bread / wold offer him a ſtone? Or if he aſked fyſh / wold he prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him a ſerpent? If ye then w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are evell / can gyue your children good giftes: howe moche more ſhall your father which is in heauen / gyue good thynges to them that aſke him? Mat .vij. a.</p>
               <p>Thou lord arte our father and Redemer and thy name is everlaſting / Eſay .xliij. c.</p>
               <p>I prayſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / o father and lord of heauen and earth / that thou haſt hyd theſe things from the wyſe and prudent / &amp; opened the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto Babes. Euen ſo Father / for ſo it pleaſed the. All thinges are geuen over vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me of my father / and no man knoweth the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne but the father: neyther knoweth any man the father ſaue the ſonne / and he to whome the ſonne wyll open it. Mathe xi. e. Mathew .xxviij. c. Luc .x. c. Iohn .iij. e .vij. c .viij. b .x. b.</p>
               <p>Behold what loue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father hath ſhewed
<pb facs="tcp:19829:5"/> on vs / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhulde be called the chyldren of God .i. Iohn .iij. a.</p>
               <p>For ſo much then as ye are childeren / God hath ſent the ſpirit of his ſonne into your hartes / which crieth: Abba (that is) father. Wherfore nowe thou art not a ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaunte / but a ſonne. If thou be a ſonne then arte thou the heyre of God / thorowe Chriſt. Gal .iiij. a Roma .viij. b.</p>
               <p>For who ſoever are led by the ſpirite of God / are Gods Children: for ye haue not receiued the ſpyryte of / bondage to feare a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny more / but ye haue receiued the ſpyryte of adopcion / wherby we cry Abba (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye) father. The ſame ſpirite certifieth our ſpirite y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are the chyldren of God. If we be childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / then are we heyres alſo / namely the heyres of God / and heyres an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nexed with Chriſt. Roma .viij. b.</p>
               <p>Haue we not all one father? Hath not one God made vs? Why doth every one of vs then deſpyſe his owne brother / and ſo breake the Couenaunt of our Father? Malach .ij. b.</p>
               <p>Is not he thy father and thy Lorde? Hath not he made the and Prepared the? Deut .xxxij. a.</p>
               <p>Which arte in Heauen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:5"/>
               <p>And cal no man father vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aerth / for one is your father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And ye ſhall not ſuffer your ſelues to be called maſters / for one is your maſter / namely / Chriſt and all ye are brethern. Mathew .xxiij. a.</p>
               <p>Vnto the / lyft I vp mine eyes / thou y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dwelleſt in the heauens. Pſal. ciij. a.</p>
               <p>ij. Paralyp .vi. d. Eſay. lxvi. a.</p>
               <p>The lorde hath prepared hys ſeate in heauen / and his kingdom ruleth over all Pſal. cij. c. /</p>
               <p>Our God is in heauen / he doth what ſoeuer pleaſeth him. Pſal. cxv. a.</p>
               <p>All the heauens are the lordes / and the earth hath he geuen vnto men. Pſalmes. cxv. d.</p>
               <p>Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is my ſeat &amp; aerth is my foteſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le where ſhal now the houſe ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wyl buylde vnto me? &amp; wher ſhall be the place that I wil dwel in? as for theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / my hand hath made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d they are al crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted / ſayth the lord / Eſay. lxvi. a.</p>
               <p>Do not I fulfyl heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; aerth (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde) Ierem .xxiij. d.</p>
               <p>For heauen &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all heauens may not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Who am I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I ſhuld buyld hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an houſe? i. Reg .viij. d .ii
<pb facs="tcp:19829:6"/> Chron .ij. b.</p>
               <p>But ſalomon buylt him an houſe / how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit the hygheſt of all dwelleth not in tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples that are made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> handes / as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet ſayth. &amp;c. Act .vij. f.</p>
               <p>God which made the worlde / and all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therin is / for ſo moch as he is lord of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth / dwelleth not in Temples made of hands / neyther is he worſhipped with mens handes / as though he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of any man / ſeyng he hym ſelfe geueth lyfe and breath vnto al men euery where: &amp; hath made of one bloude all the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon of men to dwell vppon all the face of the Earth: and hath aſſygned borders ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted before / howe long and farre they ſhuld dwel / that they myght fele and find him. And truly he is not farre from euery one of vs / for in him we lyue / move and haue our beyng / as certeyne of your owne poetes alſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſayd: we are his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratyon. &amp;c. Act .xvij. d. and .e.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>Halowed be thy name</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:6"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>I wyll make the name of my holynes to be knowen among my people of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell / and I will not let my holy name to be euell ſpoken of any more: but the very hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then alſo ſhal knowe that I am the Lord the holy one of Iſraell. Gzech .xxxix. b.</p>
               <p>At that tyme ſhall there be one Lorde onely / and his name ſhalbe but one. 1. Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha .xiiij. b.</p>
               <p>I do not this for your ſakes (O houſe of Iſraell) but for my holy names ſake. Ezech .xxxvi. d.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:7"/>
               <p>Bring me my ſonnes from farre / &amp; my doughters from the endes of the worlde: Namelye all thoſe that call on my name. For them haue I created / faſſhyoned and made for myne honoure. Ezay .xliij. a.</p>
               <p>And the tyme ſhall come / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer calleth on the name of the lorde / ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Ioel .ij. f.</p>
               <p>O Lord our gouuernour / howe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. Pſa .viij. a</p>
               <p>From the ryſing vp of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> going down of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame / my name is great amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyles / yea in al places. Mal .i. c</p>
               <p>The lord is hye aboue all heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; his glory aboue the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Who is lyke vnto the lorde our God / that hath his dwellinge ſo hygh / whych humbleth him ſelfe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde that is in heauen and aerth? whyche taketh vp the ſymple oute of the duſt and lyfteth the poore out of the myre. The Lordes name is worthy to be prayſed, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the riſyng vp of the ſonne vnto the goyng downe of the ſame. Pſalm. cxij. a.</p>
               <p>Synge vnto the Lord and prayſe hys Name / be telling of his Saluation from day to day. Declare hys honoure amonge the heathen / and his wonders among all people. Pſalm .xcv. a.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:7"/>
               <p>The name of the Lorde is a ſtrong ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell / the ryghtuous flieth vnto it / &amp; ſhall be ſaued. Prouerb .xviij. b.</p>
               <p>Not vnto vs (O Lorde) not vnto vs: but vnto thy name geue the praiſe / for thy louynge mercy and faithfulnes. Pſalme. Cxv. a.</p>
               <p>Helpe vs (O God our Sauyour) for the glory of thy name: O deliuer vs / and forgiue vs our ſinnes for thy names ſake Pſalm. lxxviij. b.</p>
               <p>Leade my in thy way (O lord) that I walke in thy trueth. O let my harte dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te in fearing thy name. I thanke the / o Lord my God / and wyll prayſe thy name for euer Pſa. lxxxv. b. clxv. a. Chro .xxix. c</p>
               <p>A frewyll offring will I geue the / and prayſe thy law / o lord / becauſe it is ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable. Pſalm. liij. a.</p>
               <p>I will declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name vnto my brethe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ren / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middeſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion wil I prayſe the. Pſal .xxi. c .xxiij. a. Ebr .ij. c.</p>
               <p>The Lord gaue and the Lord hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye: Now bleſſed be the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. Iob .i. d.</p>
               <p>Let vs therfore by hym offer alwayes vnto God the ſacryfice of prayſe: that is to ſay the frute of thoſe lyppes which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb facs="tcp:19829:8"/> his name. Ebre .xiij. c. Pſal .xci. a.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>Thy Kingdom come</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>Seke ye fyrſt the kingdome of heauen and the ryghtuouſneſſe therof / ſo ſhall all theſe things be miniſtred vnto you. Mat vi. d. Luke .xij. d .iij Reg .iij. b.</p>
               <p>The kyngdom of God is not meate &amp; drinke but ryghtuouſneſſe / peace and ioye in the holy gooſt. Roma .xiiij. c.</p>
               <p>The kingdome of God is not in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: but in power .i. Corin .iiij. c.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:8"/>
               <p>The kyngdom of God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not wyth outwarde apperaunce / neyther ſhall it be ſayde: Lo / here or there is it, For beholde the Kyngdome of God is inward in you. Luke .xvij. c.</p>
               <p>Except a man be borne a newe / he can not ſee the kingdom of God. Ihon .iij. a.</p>
               <p>Except a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be borne of water and of the ſpirite / he can not come into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. Ihon .iij. a.</p>
               <p>Who ſoeuer receaueth not the kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of God / as a chyld / ſhall not entre ther in. Luke .xviij. b.</p>
               <p>Fleſhe and bloude can not inheret the Kingdom of God .i. Cor .xv. e.</p>
               <p>The kingdom of heauen ſuffreth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence / and the violent plucke it vnto them. Math .xi. b.</p>
               <p>Which hath deliuered vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the powr of Darkenes / and tranſlated vs into the Kyngdome of hys deare Sonne / in who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me we haue Redemption thorrowe hys Bloud / namely / the forgeuenes of ſynnes Colloſ .i. b.</p>
               <p>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kingdome vnto God the father. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall put down al rule &amp; ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / &amp; powr. For he muſt reigne til he haue
<pb facs="tcp:19829:9"/> all hys ennemies vnder fete. The laſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemye that ſhall be deſtroyed / is death / i. Cor .xv. c.</p>
               <p>Similitudes of the kingdom of God. Mathe .xxiij. a. e. Mar .iiij. a. b. Luke the viij. a. b. Math .xiij. e. Mark, iiij. d. Luke .xiij. d e. Math .xiij. f. g .xviij / c .xx. &amp; .xxij. a Lu .xiiij. d. Mat .xxv. a. b. Luk .xix. b .xv.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>Thy will be done in Earth as it is in Heauen.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>What wylt thou that I ſhall do? Act .ix. a</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:9"/>
               <p>Teach me to do the thing that pleaſeth the / for thou art my God: Let thy louyng ſpyryt leade me forth vnto the Lande of rightuouſnes. Pſal. cxlij. b.</p>
               <p>This is the will of him which hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me / that who ſoeuer ſeeth the ſonne / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leueth on him / haue everlaſtinge life / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d I ſhall rayſe hym vp at the laſt daye. Iohn .vi. e.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt do that which is ryght a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d good in the ſight of the lord / to the intent that thou mayeſt proſper. Deut .vi. b.</p>
               <p>Ye ſhall not do theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges which ſeme good in your owne eyes Deut .xij. a.</p>
               <p>A man thinketh all hys ways to be clea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / but it is the Lorde that faſhyoneth the mindes. Pro .xvi. a.</p>
               <p>My councell ſhall ſtande: and I ſhall do what ſoever pleaſeth me. Eſay / xlvi.</p>
               <p>He handeleth according to hys wyll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the powers of heauen and among the inhabytours of the earth / and there is none that maye reſyſt his hande / or ſaye: what doeſt thou? Dani / iiij. e.</p>
               <p>So lieth it not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wil or ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of God. Rom .x. b.</p>
               <p>For it is God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worketh in you both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll and the dede. Phil .ij. b.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:10"/>
               <p>He worketh all thinges after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of his owne will / that we might be to the praiſe of his glory. Ephe .i. b.</p>
               <p>Such truſt haue we thorow Chriſt to Godwarde / not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are ſufficient of our ſelves / to think any thing as of our ſelves but our ablenes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of god ij. cor .iii. a.</p>
               <p>I do not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wil / but what I hate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do I. Yf I do now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> I wil not / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law is good. Item y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> good y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I will do I not / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> evel w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> I wyl not / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do I. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I fi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wil do good / evel is preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me. For I delite in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of god after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but I ſe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other lawe in my me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres / w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ſtriueth agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the law of my minde / &amp; taketh me priſoner in the law of ſinne / w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is in my membres. O wretched man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am / who ſhall deliver me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of this death? I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k God thorow Ieſus Chriſt our lord. Roman .vij. c.</p>
               <p>He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil of God / abideth for ev<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> Iohn .v.</p>
               <p>O prayſe the lorde / ye angels of hys / ye that be mightie in ſtrength / fulfilling hys comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dment y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men may heare the voice of his words? O prayſe the lord al ye his hoſtes / ye ſeruauntes of hys / that do hys
<pb facs="tcp:19829:10"/> pleaſure. Pſal. ciij. a.</p>
               <p>Glory be vnto God an hye / and peace vppon earth and vnto men a good wyll. Luke .ij. b.</p>
               <p>Who ſaid to Cirus: thou art mine hird<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhal fulfyll all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs after my wyll. Eſay xliiij. e.</p>
               <p>I am come downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen / not to do mine owne wyll / but the wyll of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ſent me. Iohn vi. d.</p>
               <p>Sacrifice &amp; offering thou woldeſt not haue / but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt opened mine eares: burnt offrings &amp; ſacrifice for ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne thou haſt not allowed. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd I: Lo / I come in the beginning of the boke it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhuld fulfyll thy will (o my God) &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I content to do: yea the law is within my hart. Pſal .xxxix. b. Ebr .x. b.</p>
               <p>I ſeke not mine owne will / but the wil of my father w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me. Iohn v. c.</p>
               <p>Not my will / but thy wyll be fulfylled Luk .xxij. e.</p>
               <p>Foraſmoch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as Chriſt hath ſuffred for vs in the fleſh / arme your ſelves lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe with the ſame mind. For he whiche ſuffreth in the fleſh / ceaſeth from ſinne / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> henceforth (as moche time as yet remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the fleſh) he ſhuld not lyue after y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19829:11"/> luſtes of men / but after the wyll of God .i. Pet .iiij. a.</p>
               <p>Not as I will but as thou wilt. Mat xxvi. d. Mat c .xiiij. d.</p>
               <p>And faſhyon not your ſelues lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his world but be chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged thorow the renewing of your mind / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may prove what things that good that acceptable ad par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t wyll of God is. Rom .xij. a.</p>
               <p>For this is the will of God / even your ſanctifienge / that ye ſhulde abſteyne from whoredome / t at every one of you ſhulde knowe howe to kepe his veſſell in holines and honour / and not in the luſt of concupi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcence / as the heathen / whiche knowe not Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> .i. Teſſ .iiij. a.</p>
               <p>Wherfore be not ye vnwiſe / but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande what the wyll of the lorde is. Eph .v. b.</p>
               <p>Alwaies fervently laboring for you in prayers that ye may ſtand perfect &amp; ful in all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl of God. Col .iiij. b.</p>
               <p>And this is the free boldnes which we have toward him that if we aſke any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g accordinge to hys wyll / he heareth vs .i. Iohn v. b.</p>
               <p>The God of peace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> brought again fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead our lorde Ieſus the great ſhepard
<pb facs="tcp:19829:11"/> of the ſhepe / thorow the bloud of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting teſtament) make you perfect in all good workes to do hys wyll / working to you that whych is pleaſaunt in hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thorow Ieſus Chryſt to whome be pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe for euer and euer. Amen</p>
               <p>Ebre .xiij. d.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>Gyue vs this day our dayly breade.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>The bleſſing of the Lord maketh ry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h men / as for carefull and trauayle it doth nothing thervnto. Prouer .x. c.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:12"/>
               <p>He geueth foode vnto all fleſh / and his mercy endureth for euer. Pſal. cxxxv.</p>
               <p>For vnto whome ſoeuer God geueth riches / goodes and powr / he geueth it him to enioye it / to take it for hys portion / and to be refreſſhed of his labour: this is now the gifte of God. Eccle .v. d.</p>
               <p>The lorde wyll not let the ſoule of the ryghtuous ſuffer hunger / but he putteth the vngodly from hys deſyre. Proue .x. a.</p>
               <p>I haue bene yong &amp; now am olde: yet ſawe I neuer the ryghtuous forſake / nor his ſeed to ſeke theyr Breade? Pſalme .xxxvi. d.</p>
               <p>Who prouideth meate for the Rauen / when hys yong ones crye vnto God / and flye about for want of meat. Iob .xxxviij d.</p>
               <p>Whych geueth foder vnto the catell / &amp; fedeth the yong Rauens that call vppon hym. Pſalm. cxlvi. b</p>
               <p>Yea and the yong lyons / whych roare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the praye / and ſeke their meate at God Pſalm. ciij. c</p>
               <p>They wayte all vppon the / that thou mayeſt geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meate in due ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> geueſt it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / they gather it: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> openeſt thine ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / they are filled w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> good. Pſa. cii</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:12"/>
               <p>O caſt thy burthen or care vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord / and he ſhall noriſh the. Pſal. liiij. c.</p>
               <p>Caſt all your care on hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / for he careth for you .i. Petr .v. a.</p>
               <p>Be not careful but in al things let your peticions in prayer and ſupplycacion / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of thankes / be knowne before God Philip .iiij.</p>
               <p>Therfore I ſaye vnto you be not ye carefull for your life / what ye ſhall eate or what ye ſhall Dryncke: nor yet for youre body what ye ſhall put on / is not the lyfe more worth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meate &amp; the body more of value then rayme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foules of the ayer: for they ſow not / neither repe nor yet cary into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> barnes: &amp; yet your hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly father fedeth them. Are ye not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they? Which of you (though he toke thought therfor) could put one cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bit vnto his ſtature? why care ye then for raiment? Conſider the Lilies of the Feld howe they grow. They laboure not / neither Spinne. And yet for all that I ſaye vnto you / that even Salomon in all his royaltie was not arayed like vnto one of theſe. Wherfore if GOD ſo Cloth the Graſſe / whyche is to Daye in the Felde / and to morrow ſhalbe caſt into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furnace / 
<pb facs="tcp:19829:13"/> ſhall he not moch more do the ſame vnto you / o ye of lytle faith? Therfore take no thought / ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: what ſhal we eat / or what ſhall we drink? or wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall we be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed? After al ſuch do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathen ſeke / For your heuenly father knoweth / that ye ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue nede of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe thinges. Seke ye fyrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the righteouſneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe therof / and al theſe thynges ſhall be mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtred vnto you. Math .vi. d.</p>
               <p>Care not then for to morrowe / for the morrow ſhall care for it ſelfe: Euery daye hath ynough of his own trauayle. Ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A praier of Salomon for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lyuing.</note>Two things will I require of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / that thou wylt not deny me before I dye. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue from me vanyce and lyes: geue me neyther beggery nor ryches / onely grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me a neceſſary lyuing. Leaſt if I be to ful I denye the / and ſaye: what felowe is the Lord? And leaſt I being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned thorow pouerte / fall vnto ſtealing / &amp; for ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of my God Prouerb .xxx. a</p>
               <p>If ryches encreaſe / ſet not your harte vppon them. Pſal. lxi. b.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:13"/>
               <head>And forgyue vs our treſpaſſes.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>It is I / It is I onely / that for myne owne ſelf ſake do away thyne offences / &amp; forget thy Sinnes: ſo that I wyll neuer thynke vppon them. Eſay .xliij. d.</p>
               <p>As for thyne offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces / I dryue them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way lyke the Cloudes / and thy ſinnes as the myſt. Turne the againe vnto me / and I wyll delyuer the. Eſay .xliiij. d</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:14"/>
               <p>The lord is full of compaſſion a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy / long ſufferinge and of great goodnes. He will not alwaye be chydinge / neyther wyll he kepe his angre for euer. He hath not delt with vs after our ſynnes / nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded vs according to oure wickednes. For loke how hye the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is / in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the earth / ſo great is his mercy alſo towards them that feare him. Loke how wyde the Eaſt is from the Weſt / ſo farre hath he ſet our ſinnes from vs. Yea lyke as a father pitieth hys owne children / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo is the Lorde mercifull vnto them that feare him: For he knoweth wherof we be made. He Remembreth that we are but duſt. Pſalm. cij. a.</p>
               <p>Shame not to confeſſe thine errour / &amp; ſubmit not thy ſelf vnto every man / becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of ſinne. Eccle .iiij. d.</p>
               <p>If we ſay that we have no ſinne / we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue our ſelues / and the trueth is not in vs. But if we knowledg our ſinnes / God is faithfull and luſt to forgiue vs our ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / and to clenſe vs from all vnryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. If we ſay we haue not ſinned / we make him a lyer / and hys worde is not in vs .i. Iohn .i.</p>
               <p>Who can ſay: my hart is cleane / I am
<pb facs="tcp:19829:14"/> innocent from ſinne?</p>
               <p>Ther is not one rightuous man in al y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> aerth / that doth good and ſinneth not. Ecc vij. c .i. Reg .viij. e. Pſal. liij. a. Rom .iij. b.</p>
               <p>The rightuous falleth .vij. times. Pro xxiiij. c.</p>
               <p>What is man / that he ſhuld be vncleane / what hath he w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is born of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by he might be knowne to be rightuous. Beholde / he hath found vnfaithfulnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his owne ſaintes: yea the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens are vncleane in his ſight. How mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an abhominable &amp; vyle man whiche drinketh wickednes lyke water? Iob .iiij. b .xv. b .xxv. b.</p>
               <p>Who can tell how oft he offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth? Oh clence thou me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſecret fautes. Pſal .xviij. b.</p>
               <p>I turned me vnto God the lorde for to pray &amp; make mine i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / ſak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cloth &amp; aſſhes. I prayed before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord my God &amp; knowledge / ſaying: O lorde / thou great &amp; fearefull God / thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kepeſt coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunt and mercy with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which loue the a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d do thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes. Dan .ix. a.</p>
               <p>Therfore I confeſſed my ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / &amp; hyd not mine vnrightuouſnes. I ſayd / I will knowledge myne offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; accuſe my
<pb facs="tcp:19829:15"/> ſelfe vnto the Lord / and ſo thou forgeueſt me the wyckednes of my ſynne. Pſalme .xviij. d .xxxi. a.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy vppon me (O God) after thy goodnes / and according vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great mercyes do awaye myne offences. Waſh me well from my wyckednes and clenſe me from my ſynne. For I knowledge my fautes / and my ſynne is euer before me.</p>
               <p>Againſt the onely / againſt the haue I ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / and done euell in thy ſyght. Pſalme. L. a</p>
               <p>Conuert thou me / and I ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted: for thou art my Lord God. Iere .xxxi. c. Pſalm. lxxx. a.</p>
               <p>O reconcile me wyth Iſope / &amp; I ſhall be clene: waſh thou me / and I ſhalbe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſnowe. Pſalm. l. a.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>As we forgiue them that treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs.</head>
               <p>Yf you forgyue other men theyr treſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / your heauenly father ſhall alſo forgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue you. But and ye wyll not forgyue men theyr treſpaces no more ſhall your father
<pb facs="tcp:19829:15"/> forgiue you your treſpaces. Math .vi. b. Luk xi. d.</p>
               <p>Forgiue &amp; it ſhalbe forgeuen vnto you Luk .vi. f.</p>
               <p>Whan thou offreſt thy gift at the alter / &amp; there remembreſt that thy brother hath ought agaynſt the. Leave there thyne of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring before the allie / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d go thy way fyrſt and reconcile thy ſelfe to thy brother / and then come and offer thy gyft. Agree with thyne aduerſary quickly whyle y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye wyth him / leaſt that aduerſary dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the to the iudge / and the iudge deliuer the to the myniſter / and then thou be caſt into priſon. I ſaye vnto the verelye / thou ſhalt not come oute thence / tyll thou have payde the vtter muſt farthinge. Mathew v. c.</p>
               <p>Yf thy brother treſpace againſt the / god and tell him his faut betwene the and him alone. Item ſo ſhall my heauenly Father do alſo vnto you / yf ye everye one of you from your hartes / forgeue not hys Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his treſpaces. Mat .xviij. c. d. Luke .xvij. a.</p>
               <p>Knowledge your fautes one to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other and pray one for an other. Iacob .v. c.</p>
               <p>Forbearing one an other / and forgeui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:19829:16"/> one an other / if any man haue a quarell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an other. Lyke as Chryſt hath for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geuen you: euen ſo ye alſo. Colloſſ .iij. b.</p>
               <p>Bleſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that curſe you: praye for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wrongfully trouble you. Luke .vi. c.</p>
               <p>Praye for them whych do you wrong &amp; perſecute you / that ye maye be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your Father whiche is in heauen. For he maketh hys ſonne to aryſe on the euell and on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good: and ſendeth hys tayne on the iuſte and vniuſte. Math .v. e.</p>
               <p>Ieſus Chriſt ſayd) Father forgiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for they wote not what they doo. Luke / xxiij. c.</p>
               <p>Saint Stephen ſayde / Laye not thys ſynne to theyr charge. Acte .vij. g.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>And leade vs not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:16"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>Of two kindes of temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wherof the fyrſt followynge / is Approbacion of fayth.</p>
               <p>My brethern / cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te it exceding ioy whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye fall into diuers temptacions / for aſmo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as ye knowe / howe that the tryeng of your fayth bringeth pacience. Iacob .i. a. Roma .v. a.</p>
               <p>Happy is the man that indureth in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacion / for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is tryed / he ſhal receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croune of lyfe / w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the lord hath promiſed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that love him. Iames .i. b.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:17"/>
               <p>My ſonne / diſpiſe not the chaſtening of the lorde / neyther faynt when thou art re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buked of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For whome the lord loueth / hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he chaſteneth / and yet he delyteth in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen as a father in his owne ſonne. Pro iij. b.</p>
               <p>The oue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proveth the potters veſſell / ſo doth temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of trouble trye rightuous men. Eccle .xxvij. b.</p>
               <p>Examen me (o lord) and proue me / trye out my reynes and my hart. Pſal .xxv. a.</p>
               <p>My grace is ſufficient for the. For ſtrength is made perfect thorow weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes .ij. Cor .xij. a.</p>
               <p>God is faithfull which ſhall not ſuffre you to be tempted aboue youre ſtrengthe but ſhall in the middeſt of the temptacion make away to come out / that ye may bear it .i. Cor .x. b.</p>
               <p>The lorde knoweth how to deliuer the Godly out of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacion .ij. Pet .ij. b.</p>
               <p>As for you / ye are they that haue bidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me in temptacions. Luk .xxij. b.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>Of the other temptacion which we require to avoyde.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:17"/>
               <p>Watch and praye / that ye fall not into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacyon: the ſpiryt is willyng but the fleſh is weake. Math .xxvi. d. Marc .xiiij. d</p>
               <p>Let no man ſaye / when he is tempted / that he is tempted of God. For God tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth not vnto euell: Neyther tempteth he any man / but euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is tempted drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away and entiſed of his owne concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. Then when luſte hath conceaued / ſhe bringeth forth ſinne / and ſinne when it is finiſſhed bringeth forth death. Iacob .i. b</p>
               <p>They that will be rich / fall into the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion and ſnare and into many folyſh / &amp; noiſome luſtes .i. Timo .vi. b.</p>
               <p>Conſyder thyne owne ſelfe / that thou alſo be not tempted. Galla .vi. a.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>But delyuer vs from the Euell.</head>
               <p>Be ſober / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d watch / for your aduerſary the deuell walketh aboue as a roaring lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeking whome he may deuoure: Whome reſyſt ſtedefaſt in the faith / and knowe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your Bretheren in the woorld / haue euen the ſame afflictions .i. Ptri .v. b. Pſalm. Liiij. d.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:18"/>
               <p>Sathan hath deſired after you / that he myght ſifte you euen as wheate: but I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue prayed for the / that thy fayth fayle not. And when thou arte conuerted / ſtrength thy brethern. Luke .xxij. c.</p>
               <p>I ſent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I might haue knowledge of your Faith / leaſt haplye the tempter had tempted you / &amp; leaſt oure labour had bene in vaine .i. Teſſ .iij. a</p>
               <p>We knowe that who ſoeuer is borne of God / ſinneth not. but he that is begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God / he kepeth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth him not .i. Iohn .v. c.</p>
               <p>For all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is borne of God ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the world / eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our faith .i. Iohn .v. a.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>For thyne is the kyngdome a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the power / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for euer. Amen</head>
               <p>O lord God of Iſrael our father / pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed be thou now and euermore. O Lorde thine is the might / power / glory / victorye and the prayſe. For all that which is in heauen and aerth / is thyne. O lord thyne is the kyngdome / &amp; thou art Prince of all thinges. Thyne are the rycheſſes / treaſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res / honour and dominion ouer all. And
<pb facs="tcp:19829:18"/> in thy handes is the vertue / might / power excellencye Empyre and rule vppon and aboue all thinges. Wherfore nowe oure God / we giue laud praiſe and glory to thy moſt noble name .i. Chroni .xxix. c.</p>
               <p>Read the whole. Pſalm. cxliiij.</p>
               <p>O the depenes of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God? How in comprehenſible are his iudgementes / and his waies vnſearcheable? For who hath known the mynd of the lord? or who hath bene his councell gever? Or who hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him ought aforehand that he myght be recompenſed againe? For of him / and thorowe him / and in him are all thinges. To him be praiſe for euer. Rom .xi. d.</p>
               <p>To God only wiſe / our Sauiour / be glory &amp; magnificence / Empire and powr / now and euermore. Amen. Iudic .i. g. Rom .xi. d .ij. Tim .vi. d .i. Petr .v. d. Apo .v. d .vij. c.</p>
               <p>Thou art worthy (o lord) to receiue glory and honour / and power For thou haſt created all thynges / and for thy wylles ſake they are and were created. Apo .iiij. b</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:19"/>
               <head>¶The ſomme of the Prayer. Our Father whych arte in heauen. Hallowed be thy name.</head>
               <p>O Lord God our father in heauen / we thy myſerable children vppon aerth / beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the / that thou wylt mercyfully Looke on vs / and lende vs thy grace / that thy na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me may be ſanctyfyed amonge vs / and in al the world / thorow the pure and ſincere teachyng of thy word / and thorow aerneſt charite in our daily lyuing and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. Seclude thou gratyouſlye all falſe doctrine &amp; euell lyuing / wherby thy wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy name / might be blaſphemed and ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>Thy kyngdome Come.</head>
               <p>O let thy kyngdom come and be graet. All ſynfull / blynd people and ſuche as are holden captyue of the deuell in hys kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome / thoſe brynge y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> to the knowleadge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true faith / in Ieſus Chryſt thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:19"/>
               <head>Thy wyll be done in earth as it is in Heauen.</head>
               <p>Strength vs Lorde wyth thy ſpirite / to do &amp; to ſuffer thy wyll both in lyfe and death in wel and woo / that our will may alway be broken / offred vp &amp; mortified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>Gyue vs thys Daye our Daylye Breade.</head>
               <p>And geue vs our dayly bread. Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs from couetous deſyre / and careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the belly: that of the / we maye be aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſured to haue Aboundaunce of all good thynges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>And forgeue vs our treſpaces / as we forgyue them that treſpas againſt vs.</head>
               <p>Forgyue vs our treſpace / as we forgi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue them whych offend vs: that our harte maye haue a ſure and glad co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience / and that we neuer feare nor be afrayde for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:20"/>
               <head>And let vs not be led into temptacion.</head>
               <p>Lead vs not into temptacion / but help vs thorow thy ſpirite / to ſubdue the fleſh / to deſpiſe the world with his vanities / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ouercome the deuel wyth all his crafty aſſaultes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>But Delyuer vs from euell.</head>
               <p>And fynally deliuer thou vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al euell both bodely and goſtly / temporall a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d aeter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall. Amen.</p>
               <p>All they that aerneſtlye deſyre thys / let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaye. Amen. Beleuing wythout any doubte that it is heard in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge as Chriſt promiſed vs ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye pray beleue aſſuredly that ye ſhall haue it / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it ſhall come to paſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The ſomme of the prayer</head>
               <p>Seke ye fyrſt the kingdome of God / &amp; al theſe things ſhalbe miniſtred vnto you Luke .xiiij. d.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis</trailer>
            <trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:19829:20"/>
               <figure>
                  <p>VERBVM DEI</p>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Proue the ſpyrites / whether they be of God.</p>
                  <bibl>Ihon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iiij .i. Reg .viij. d. Mat .vij.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
